Aurèle Toussaint 2018/11/14

Curriculum Vitae

Aurèle TOUSSAINT PhD

Date of birth: 16th of July 1988

Nationality: French

Professional address:

Institute of Ecology and Earth Sciences Department of Botany Lai 40 Tartu 51005 ESTONIA

E-mail: toussaint.aurele@gmail.com

Current position

September 2016 – Present: Research fellow

Research done at the Institute of Ecology and Earth Sciences, Departement of Botany (University of Tartu, Estonia)

Supported by the Estonian Research Council (MOBJD-276).

Evolved in the project: *IUT20-29: Dark diversity: taxonomic, phylogenetic, functional and genetic levels in dynamic plant communities.*

Professional appointments

October 2012 – June 2016: PhD in Fish Macro-ecology

Research done at the Laboratory 'Evolution & Diversité Biologique' (University Paul Sabatier – Toulouse 3 UMR 5174)

Topic: Functional diversity of freshwater fish fauna at the world scale: patterns, determinants and human activities impacts

Supervisors: Pr. Sébastien Brosse (University Paul Sabatier) and Dr. Sébastien Villéger (University Montpellier 2)

January 2016 – June 2016: Erasmus-Mundus mobility for PhD (6 months)

Research done at the Kyung Hee University – Dept of Biology – Seoul Korea **Supervisor**: Pr. Young-Seuk Park (Kyung-Hee University)

October 2013 – June 2015: Teaching assistant in biostatistics at the University Paul Sabatier – Toulouse 3.

Aurèle Toussaint 2018/11/14

Education

2011-2012: Second year of Master of Science (MSc) in Biostatistics and ecological systems modelling University Paul Sabatier-Toulouse 3, France – With second highest distinction (Rank: 5/19)

Thesis done at the Laboratory 'Evolution & Diversité Biologique' (UMR 5174) supervised by Sébastien Brosse and Sébastien Villéger.

Topic: Determinants of change in taxonomic dissimilarity in the freshwater fish fauna at the world scale

2010-2011: First year of Master of science (MSc) in Ecology at the University Paul Sabatier-Toulouse 3, France – With distinction (Rank: 43/172)

Thesis done at the Laboratory 'Evolution & Diversité Biologique' (UMR 5174) supervised by Sébastien Brosse and Simon Blanchet.

Topic: Revision of the taxonomy of the freshwater fish European fauna and implications for conservation and biogeography.

2008-2010: Bachelor of Science (BSc) in Biology of Organisms University of Lorraine, Nancy, France (Rank: 90/237)

2009, July: **Thesis** done at the 'Département d'Ecologie, Physiologie et Ethologie' (UMR 7178 DEPE) supervised by Pr. M. Trabalon & Dr. C. Gilbert.

Topic: Sexual behaviour of the rats in a choosing situation

2006-2007: 'PCEM1': First Year of the medical studies University of Lorraine in Nancy, France (Rank for the competitive examination: 888/1959)

2006: 'Baccalauréat' of Sciences (Equivalent to A-Level)

Scientific communications

Article in international peer-reviewed journals

- * Co-senior authorship
- 7. **Toussaint A.**, Charpin N., Villéger S.* & Brosse S.* Worldwide freshwater fish homogenization is driven by few widespread non-native species. *Ecology Letters* 21(11), 1649-1659
- 6. Kuczynski L., Côte J., **Toussaint A.**, Brosse S., Buisson L., Grenouillet G. (2018) Spatial mismatch in morphological, ecological and phylogenetic diversity, in historical and contemporary European freshwater fish faunas. *Ecography* 41:1665-1674.
- 5. Tedersoo L., Laanisto L., Rahimlou S., **Toussaint A.**, Hallikma T., Pärtel M. (2018) Global database of plants with root-symbiotic nitrogen fixation: Nod DB. *Journal*

Aurèle Toussaint 2018/11/14

of Vegetation Science 10:560-568

4. **Toussaint A.**, Charpin N., Brosse S.* & Villéger S.* Global functional diversity of freshwater fish is concentrated in the Neotropics. 2016. *Scientific Report* 6: 22125.

- 3. **Toussaint A.**, Beauchard O., Oberdorff T., Brosse S. & Villeger S. Worldwide freshwater fish homogenization is driven by a few widespread non-native species. 2016. *Biological Invasions* 18: 1295–1304.
- 2. Allard L., **Toussaint A.**, Vigouroux R. & Brosse S. Length-weight relationship of 58 fish species in streams of French Guiana. 2015. **Journal of Applied** *Ichthyology* 31: 567-570.
- Toussaint A., Beauchard O., Oberdorff T., Brosse S. & Villeger S. 2014. Historical assemblage distinctiveness and the introduction of widespread non-native species explain worldwide changes in freshwater fish taxonomic dissimilarity. *Global Ecology and Biogeography* 23:574–584.

Oral presentations

- 5. **Toussaint, A.**, Pärtel M. Global mismatch between the species richness of vascular plants and symbiosis fungi across biogeographic realms. *Annual meeting for macroecology of the ecological society of Germany Austria and Switzerland, Birmendorf* (Switzerland). 2018, April.
- Toussaint, A., Pärtel M. Global mismatch between the species richness of vascular plants and symbiosis fungi across biogeographic realms. 60th IAVS Annual Symposium. Palermo (Italy). 2017, June.
- 3. **Toussaint, A.**, Charpin, N., Brosse, S., Villéger, S. Functional diversity and vulnerability of freshwater fish at the global scale. *7th EAFES International Congress*. Daegu (Korea). 2016, April.
- Toussaint, A., Charpin, N., Brosse, S., Villéger, S. Introductions of non-natives freshwater fish affected differently the taxonomic and functional biodiversity facets. 9th Symposium for European freshwater sciences. Geneva (Switzerland). 2015, July
- Toussaint, A., Beauchard, O., Oberdorff, T., Brosse, S., Villéger, S. Historical assemblage distinctiveness and the introduction of widespread non-native species explain worldwide changes in freshwater fish taxonomic dissimilarity. 8th Symposium for European freshwater sciences. Munster (Germany). 2013, July

Poster

1. **Toussaint, A.,** Charpin, N., Brosse, S., Villéger, S. Functional diversity of the freshwater fish fauna. *7th Biennal conference of the International Biogeography Society.* Bayreuth (Germany). *2015, January*

Aurèle Toussaint 2018/11/14

Teaching

Teaching assistant (2013-2015), University Paul Sabatier – Toulouse 3 – France

Ecology & Quantitative Biology (BSc degree) Biostatistics (BSc degree)

Multivariate analyses (MSc degree)

Student supervision

Adrien Solacroup. Master. January to April 2014. Characterization of the morphological intra specific variability on the French Guyana and European freshwater fish community.

Scientific activities

Reviewer for international peer-reviewed journals

International Journal of Biodiversity and Conservation (1 review); Biological Journal of the Linnean Society (1 review); Hydrobiologia (3 review); Ecology (1 review); Scientific Report (1 review); New Phytologist (1 review)

Languages

French: mother tongue

English: excellent command

German: basic communication skills Italian: basic communication skills

Skills

- Office software (Windows/Linux/Mac)
- Statistical analyses, function programming and high level graphics R
- Good knowledge in GIS (ArcGIS)
- Image processing
- **Driving licence**